<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Science &#8211; KIRUS.me</title>
	<atom:link href="https://Suneba.github.io/category/science/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://Suneba.github.io</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 10:54:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.0</generator>
	<item>
		<title>MALE BIRTH CONTROL IS AT OUR FINGERTIPS. WILL WE EVER GRASP IT?</title>
		<link>https://Suneba.github.io/2022/07/04/male-birth-control-is-at-our-fingertips-will-we-ever-grasp-it/</link>
					<comments>https://Suneba.github.io/2022/07/04/male-birth-control-is-at-our-fingertips-will-we-ever-grasp-it/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 10:52:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://Suneba.github.io/?p=39</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WHEN SETH KINAST STARTED TAKING AN EXPERIMENTAL MALE BIRTH CONTROL, HIS ENERGY LEVELS SHOT UP. HE NO LONGER CRASHED IN THE AFTERNOON AND HIS SEX]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-vivid-green-cyan-background-color has-background">WHEN SETH KINAST STARTED TAKING AN EXPERIMENTAL MALE BIRTH CONTROL, HIS ENERGY LEVELS SHOT UP. HE NO LONGER CRASHED IN THE AFTERNOON AND HIS SEX DRIVE IMPROVED DRAMATICALLY.</p>



<p>“We joke that it was like he was a teenager again,” says Caitlin Kinast, Seth’s partner.</p>



<p>Caitlin Kinast, a 34-year-old full-time mother of two in suburban Seattle,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.inverse.com/article/54007-why-some-birth-control-doesn-t-work">stopped using all</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.inverse.com/article/60571-your-brain-on-birth-control">hormonal birth control</a>&nbsp;after suffering a bilateral pulmonary embolism in 2013. After the birth of her and Seth’s first child in 2018, she got a copper IUD, but that gave her “periods on steroids,” she says.</p>



<p>When she and Seth learned about a clinical trial for male birth control in May 2019, they leaped at the opportunity.</p>



<p>Seth, 34, a software engineer, spent 16 months on the new birth control, which comes in a gel that users apply to their back. It’s called NES/T (“nes-tee”) after its two components, nestorone and testosterone.</p>



<p>The National Institutes of Health (NIH) is in the final year of enrollment of&nbsp;<a href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT03452111" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NES/T’s Phase 2 clinical trial</a>, which began in 2018 and involves about 420 monogamous couples at 15 sites around the world. It’s estimated to be completed in 2023 or 2024 with a Phase 3 trial beginning soon after. The participants use the gel as their only form of birth control for a year. If the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approves this progress, NES/T will become the first hormonal male contraceptive to enter Phase 3 clinical trials.</p>



<p>To say it has been a long time coming is an understatement. There’s a glaring lack of reliable reversible&nbsp;<a href="https://www.inverse.com/article/61443-birth-control-pills-side-effects-brain">contraceptives</a>&nbsp;for men* while a buffet of pills, patches, implants, and more are available to women**, along with their myriad side effects. Right now, men have just two birth control options, both non-hormonal: condoms and vasectomy. One of those has an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.plannedparenthood.org/learn/birth-control/condom/how-effective-are-condoms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">85 percent effectiveness rate</a>, and many people choose to forego it. The other one is a permanent surgical procedure.</p>



<p>On June 24, 2022, the Supreme Court overturned Roe v. Wade, effectively ending Americans’ constitutional right to abortion. With safe, legal abortion no longer available to all Americans, everyone deserves a tool to create responsible sexual partners in pregnancy prevention. What has it taken so long and are we close to an effective and safe male birth control?</p>



<p><em>*Those who produce sperm — while women and men will be shorthand for these terms in this piece, some men don’t produce sperm,&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/klinefelter-syndrome/symptoms-causes/syc-20353949" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>have XY chromosomes</em></a><em>, or two testicles, and some women don’t ovulate, have XX chromosomes, or a&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/hysterectomy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>uterus</em></a><em>&nbsp;— whether they’re queer,&nbsp;</em><a href="https://medlineplus.gov/ency/article/001669.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>intersex</em></a><em>, and/or have a condition that affects their reproductive traits.</em></p>



<p><em>**Those who ovulate.</em></p>



<h2>A HISTORY OF BIRTH CONTROL</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="https://imgix.bustle.com/uploads/getty/2022/6/30/d94f76a0-26e1-417a-b375-776534d907e5-getty-1398007155.jpg?w=1000&amp;h=667&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;duotone=93b940%2Cffffff" alt="Woman hands opening birth control pills in hand. Eating Contraceptive Pill."/><figcaption>It might come as a surprise that research behind hormonal male birth control is about as old as the pill.boytaro Thongbun / 500px/500Px Plus/Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p>For many, the name Margaret Sanger is synonymous with birth control. A first-wave feminist, Sanger opened the country’s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.plannedparenthood.org/files/1514/3518/7100/Pill_History_FactSheet.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">first birth control clinic</a>&nbsp;in 1916. In the 1940s and ‘50s, she followed the scientific development of birth control, throwing her weight and money behind research efforts. In 1960, the FDA approved the sale of an oral contraceptive. By 1965, 25 percent of married women under 45 had tried it, signaling a new era for women having greater power over their reproductive system.</p>



<p><em>(<a href="https://www.inverse.com/mind-body/the-global-condom-shortage-is-already-upon-us-how-coronavirus-is-crippling-the-contraceptive-industry">Hormonal contraceptives</a>&nbsp;are any methods that release hormones to alter the body’s reproductive cycle. Patches, pills, implants, injections, vaginal rings, and hormonal IUDs are all hormonal birth control. Non-hormonal methods such as condoms, the sponge, copper IUDs, spermicide, cervical caps, and diaphragms physically prevent the sperm from fertilizing the egg without changing the body.)</em></p>



<p>It might come as a surprise that research behind hormonal&nbsp;<a href="https://www.inverse.com/article/31600-birth-control-contraception-plant-folk-medicine-sperm-block-egg"><em>male</em>&nbsp;birth control</a>&nbsp;is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4762912/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">about as old as the pill</a>. Over the past few decades, there have been a few promising reversible non-hormonal candidates, such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7017607/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RISUG</a>, which stands for Reversible Inhibition of Sperm Under Guidance. Developed&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/43211/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">in India in the 1970s</a>, this contraceptive is a gel polymer injected to temporarily block sperm from the vas deferens (the duct that carries sperm to the urethra). A similar product,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.revolutioncontraceptives.com/vasalgel/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Vasalgel</a>, is being studied in the United States by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.revolutioncontraceptives.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Revolution Contraceptives</a>. There’s also a pill currently known as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.acs.org/content/acs/en/pressroom/newsreleases/2022/march/non-hormonal-pill-could-soon-expand-mens-birth-control-options.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YCT529,</a>&nbsp;which has prevented pregnancy in mice by disabling a vitamin A receptor, temporarily sterilizing males. Researchers may begin trials on this drug as early as the end of 2022.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>PHARMACEUTICAL COMPANIES HAVE A BUILT-IN MARKET FOR FEMALE CONTRACEPTIVES, BUT CHOOSING TO FOREGO MALE BIRTH CONTROL ALTOGETHER COULD SEAL A DOOR THEY HAVEN’T EVEN OPENED.</p></blockquote>



<p>Today, it takes a long time for most drugs to reach the market. For contraceptives, in particular, it takes about 25 years,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.popcouncil.org/research/expert/john-townsend" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">John Townsend</a>, chair of the Population Council’s ethical review board, tells&nbsp;<em>Inverse</em>. That encompasses getting it through three clinical trial stages, passing regulatory requirements, and then bringing it to market. The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.popcouncil.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Population Council</a>, a reproductive health non-profit collaborated in and helped fund the NES/T trial.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="https://imgix.bustle.com/uploads/getty/2022/6/28/95ec08df-8545-4a95-8860-da3188035b58-getty-1383520780.jpg?w=1000&amp;h=667&amp;fit=max&amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;duotone=93b940%2Cffffff" alt="Condoms ready to use in female hand, give condom safe sex concept on the bed Prevent infection and C..."/><figcaption>Right now, men have just two birth control options, both non-hormonal: condoms and vasectomy. One of those has an&nbsp;<a href="https://www.plannedparenthood.org/learn/birth-control/condom/how-effective-are-condoms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">85 percent effectiveness rate</a>, and many people choose to forego it. The other one is a permanent surgical procedure.boytaro Thongbun / 500px/500Px Plus/Getty Images</figcaption></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.malecontraception.center/_files/ugd/04e77e_1336208f99154a9ca97ad7ee96671412.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NES/T</a>&nbsp;has been in the works for at least eight years. The male contraceptive gel combines two existing hormones: testosterone and segesterone acetate (a synthetic progesterone, or progestin), aka nestorone. Doctors regularly prescribe testosterone gel for those with hypogonadism, meaning they have naturally low testosterone levels. A vaginal ring already uses nestorone as hormonal birth control. The two of them form a hand sanitizer-like gel that’s absorbed through the skin over two hours.</p>



<p>Once absorbed, the nestorone modifies the production of hormones called&nbsp;<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31644163/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gonadotropins</a>&nbsp;that come from a pea-sized gland in the brain called the pituitary gland. The nestorone suppresses the creation of two specific gonadotropins called follicle-stimulating hormone, which promotes sperm creation — of which men create about 20 to 30 million per day — and luteinizing hormone, which stimulates testosterone in the testes. This suppression results in a steep decrease of testosterone in the testicles and profound sperm suppression.</p>



<p>When taken continuously, the gel is both effective and reversible.</p>



<p>Like all participants, Seth and Caitlin Kinast were part of the trial for 20 months. For the first four months, Seth rubbed NES/T on his back and shoulders every day while the couple continued using other forms of birth control. This initial period, called the suppression phase, allows the hormones in the gel to decrease the body’s overall sperm production, but the patient is still fertile. Once sperm counts decreased to fewer than 1 million sperm per milliliter of semen, doctors gave the go-ahead for Seth and Caitlin Kinast to use NES/T as their only contraceptive for one year.</p>



<p>During that time, he had zero negative side effects, and she didn’t get pregnant.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.uwmedicine.org/bios/stephanie-page" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stephanie Page</a>, an endocrinologist at the University of Washington School of Medicine, runs a NES/T trial site in Seattle and is the primary investigator for the entire Phase 2 trial. Because the trials are still ongoing, Page could not provide a precise answer for how effective NES/T is. Though, so far, she says, her team has been “extremely encouraged by the results.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://Suneba.github.io/2022/07/04/male-birth-control-is-at-our-fingertips-will-we-ever-grasp-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
